树 屋
字 幕 组
电 影 组
郑重声明:本作品之片源、字幕均来自互联网 版权归原电影公司所有任何组织和个人不得公开传播或用于任何商业盈利用途 否则一切后果由该组织或个人承担！本字幕组和制作者不承担任何法律及连带责任！请自觉于下载后24小时内删除如果喜欢本片 请购买正版！
- Father! - Mary!
- 父亲! - 玛丽!
Papa!
爸爸!
I know you have little for yourself, Father.
父亲 我知道您过得很艰难
Promise me you'll take care of Nello?
但请您答应我 会替我照顾好尼洛 好吗?
Do you still have my drawings?
你那儿还有我的画吗?
Yes.
有的
Please give them to my boy...
请把它们留给我的儿子
to help him remember me.
让他能记住我
Even when I'm gone...
就算我去了天堂...
I'll be watching over you
我也会时时保佑你
my little masterpiece.
我的心肝宝贝
God has so much planned for you.
上帝已为你计划好了一切
I love you.
我爱你
I love you, Nello.
我爱你 尼洛
I'll always be with you.
我永远都和你在一起
翻译 主程序 冰儿 静子
校对 墨玺 惊蛰
时间轴/特效 阿贝
压制 小新
片名 义犬报恩
Can you hear your mother?
你听到你母亲说话了吗?
You must listen with your heart.
你得用你的心去听
She talks through your God-given talent.You even make me look good!
神赐予你天赋使你能跟她讲话 你甚至都让我看上去年轻不少
Come on! I'll race you to the village.
来吧! 我们看谁先跑回村子里
Come on!
快点!
- I'll beat you, Grandpa! - Look at him go.
-我肯定跑得比你快 爷爷! -瞧你跑得多快
I'll beat you!
我要得第一啦!
- Here you are, Nello. - Thank you.
-给你 尼洛 -谢谢
Good day.
日安
- Good morning, madam. - Hello. And good day to you, sir.
-早上好 女士 -你好 也祝你有愉快的一天 小先生
What have you been up to now?
你最近做什么呢?
Have you forgotten how old you are?
你这把老骨头有多脆都给你玩忘记了吧?
Oh, yeah.
噢 是的
I prefer to think of my spirit as ageless.
我更愿意认为我精神不老
- Here. - No, no. The boy, the boy.
-给你钱 -不 不 给那孩子 他是掌柜的
Thank you, sir.
谢谢你 小先生
If you please.
请收下吧
Thank you, ma'am.
谢谢您 女士
Just a moment.
稍等一下
That's for you.
这个给你
If you please.
也请收下吧
- Thank you, ma'am. - And this too.
- 太谢谢您了 女士 - 来 这个也给你
Move!
给我跑!
跑起来!
You know what, Nello?
你知道吗 尼洛?
I think tonight we'll have veal stew.Minus the veal, of course.
我想我们今天晚上能吃炖菜了 当然还是一样没有牛肉
Grandpa, look.
爷爷 看呐
Is he alive?
他还活着吗?
Barely.
就剩一口气了
Who could do such a thing?
谁会干这么残忍的事?
Some men have no respect for life.
糟蹋生命的人
This is a dog of Flanders.
这是佛兰德斯犬
A hardworking breed of dog.
是一种勤奋工作的狗
We can't just leave him here.Can we keep him?
我们不能把他留在这儿 我们能养他吗?
He can share my food.
他跟我吃一份儿就行
He's not hungry.
他还不饿呢
Well, it takes energy to eat.
这个 吃东西也是要费力气的
Leave it.
放着吧
Maybe later.
过一会儿他就吃了
What else can we do?
我们还能做些什么?
A little broth and a lot of love.
能给它点肉汤 还有爱
He's starved for both.
这两项他都缺啊
I love you so much. So you'll have to get better, okay?
我很爱你啊 所以你要快点好起来 好不好?
It's a magic necklace. It'll heal you.
这是条神奇的项链 它能治好你
What's that?
那是什么?
You should draw what you hope to see.
你应该画你想看到的东西
It's too sad, Nello.
这表情太悲伤了 尼洛
That's better.
这还差不多
Grandpa, he's drinking it! He's getting better.
爷爷 他喝东西啦 他要好起来啦
Well, I'm going to get me one of those magic necklaces!
好吧 我也要去弄一条神奇的项链
That's the spirit.
这样才对嘛
So, what do you think?
看看 你觉得怎么样?
Never underestimate the power of love,my boy.
永远别低估爱的力量 我的孩子
He needs a name.
得给他取个名字
Patrasche.
帕奇
Your mother's middle name.
是你母亲中间的名字
Then they'll both be watching over me.
这样他们俩就都能保佑我了
Grandfather, maybe you should see a doctor.
爷爷 也许你该去看看医生
For him to tell me something I already know, that I'm old and tired?
听他说我又老又虚弱? 我已经知道了啊
I know that.
我都知道的
Grandfather...
爷爷...
you're never going to die and leave me like Mother, are you?
你不会去世的 也不会像我母亲一样抛弃我的对吧
Why don't you take Patrasche and introduce him to Aloise?
你为什么去不带帕奇去找阿洛伊斯玩呢?
No, I'd rather stay here with you.
不 我更想在这儿陪着你
Come on. Go. Have fun.
去吧 去吧 好好玩
You're becoming an old man, like me.
你在家都快憋成我这个老头子了
Now we meet Aloise, my best friend.
现在我们去见见阿洛伊斯 我最好的朋友
Don't worry.She's not a dog. She's just a girl.
别担心 她不是一条狗 她是个人类女孩儿
Hi, Aloise.
嗨 阿洛伊斯
Hi, Nello.
嗨 尼洛
Whose dog is it?
这条狗是谁的?
Mine. Aloise, meet Patrasche,my new best friend.
是我的 阿洛伊斯 来见见我新的最好的朋友帕奇
I thought I was your best friend.
我还以为我是你最好的朋友呢
I mean my best dog friend. Just like Posche is your best horse friend.
我的意思是他是我最好的狗狗朋友 就像波什是你最好的马朋友一样
Okay, sounds reasonable.
好吧 这还差不多
Nello, how come you never go to school?
尼洛 你怎么会从来没上过学啊
I don't know.
我也不知道
Is it because you have to help your grandfather?
是因为你要给你爷爷帮忙吗?
I like helping Grandpa.
我喜欢帮我爷爷
Besides, who cares about books anyway?
还有 谁会想去看书啊?
Grandpa?
爷爷?
I seem to be more trouble than help these days.
这几天我简直就像个累赘一样
You're no trouble.
你才不是累赘
You just need a magic necklace too. I got you a present.
你只是也需要一条魔法项链 我给你带了礼物
I got you a present too.
我也有个礼物要送给你
This was your mother's.
这是你母亲的遗物
She wanted you to have it so you would always remember her.
她想让你保留着 这样你就能永远记住她了
Look at this.
看看这个
Seems like yesterday I was walking along the canal with your mother.
想想和你妈妈一起在运河边散步 就好像是发生在昨天一样
This was your mother's favorite place.
这曾是你妈妈最喜欢的地方
Yes, God gave your mother a wonderful talent.
是的 上帝给予了你妈妈一项完美的天赋
Just like you.
就像你一样
That looks like the statue of the man by the cathedral.
这个看起来好像是教堂旁边那个男人的雕像
It's Peter Paul Rubens.Your mother's hero.
这是彼得·保罗·鲁本斯 他可是你妈妈的英雄
*彼得·保罗·鲁本斯是一名佛兰德斯画家 巴洛克画派早期的代表人物
This was your grandmother, Rosa.
这是你的奶奶罗莎
Influenza took her from me.
流感从我身边夺走了她
But, that is my favorite picture.
但这个才是我最喜欢的一幅画
Your mother drew that for my birthday.
你妈妈在我生日的那天画给我的
I wish I could've known Mother.
我好想能多了解些妈妈的事啊
- Well... - Why did she leave the village?
- 这个嘛... - 当初她为什么要离开村子呢?
Well...
这个...
She fell in love. She met your father.
那时她坠入爱河 遇见了你的父亲
- Did you know him well? My father? - Well, your mother was...
-你很了解他吗? 我的父亲? -这个 你妈妈...
She was very secretive about her love.
你妈妈那时对她的爱情守口如瓶
You know, she had her own mind.
你知道 她是一个很有主见的人
She never told me who your father was,but...
她从来没有向我说起过你的父亲是谁 但是...
well, she loved him dearly. Yes.
她十分爱他 毫无疑问
But were they in love?
但是他们恋爱了吗?
Of course.
当然啦
Of course they were in love.
当然他们相爱了
Why would you think they weren't?
为什么你觉得他们没有呢?
Of course.
当然有啦
And, you know, she told me that he was... He was a very good man.
还有 你知道吗 她告诉我他是个...是个非常好的人
Not feeling too well again, Jehan?
感觉又快死了对吧 约翰?
Just a touch of gout.
只是有点痛风罢了
- I'll be fine. - Good.
-我会好起来的 -那就好
Now, where's my rent?
那么 你的房租呢?
I have most of it, Master Stephens.
快筹齐了 斯蒂芬斯大人
This is all?
就这么点?
We'll pay you, Master Stephens.We always do.
我们会付房租的 斯蒂芬斯大人 我们一直都没欠过
You better had.Sadly, patience is one virtue...
你们最好快点凑 唉 耐心这种美德呢...
I do not possess.
我从来没有
Good evening, gentlemen.
晚安 先生们
- I hate him. - No, you never hate.
-我恨他 -不 你不应该恨
Never lower yourself to the level of people like that.
永远别把自己贬低得像他一样
Yes, Grandpa.
知道了 爷爷
Cheer up, Nello
开心点 尼洛
Give me a smile
笑一个嘛
Where's that smile
我熟悉的
I used to know
那个笑容呢
Soon skies are going to clear up, Nello
一切都会好起来的
Cheer up, Nello
开心点 尼洛
Just be
做真正的
Glad you're you
你自己
Patrasche
帕奇
Patrasche, Cut it out.
帕奇 别叫了
What is it?
怎么回事?
Crazy dog!
你这小疯狗
- He wants to help. - That's his nature.
-他想给我们帮忙呢 -这是他的天性啊
That is a dog's dog.
可真是条任劳任怨的狗
Don't worry, Grandfather. You rest.We'll do the milk run today.
别担心 爷爷 您歇着 我们今天去送牛奶
A boy and a dog.
少年和狗狗
I don't stand a chance.
我算是没机会跟他们竞争了
There you go.
来 给你钱
Nothing like milk in the morning.
什么都比不上大清早的一口牛奶啊
He's healed up real nice.
他好得可真利索啊
You did a good job with him Nello.
你把他养的真好啊
- What's your name, dog? - Patrasche.
-你叫什么啊小狗狗? -帕奇
Well, Patrasche.
嗨 帕奇
If you're going to be seen with Nello Daas
小东西你要是想和尼洛·达斯一起出去送牛奶
and bear his dear mother's birth name
而且担得起他妈妈的姓氏的话
this rope will never do.Leave him with old William for a while.
这条破绳子可不够用 把他在这放一会儿 让老威廉给他做条新的
Go on. Go draw me a nice picture of Aloise.
去吧 去给我画张阿洛伊斯漂亮的肖像
I don't work for free, you know? We'll fix you right up here.
我可不给你白干活儿 知道吗? 我们马上就能做好
Just think...
就想象一下...
my mother once sat right here.
我妈妈曾经就这样坐在这里
Just like me.
就像现在的我一样
She was going to become a famous artist,but then she got sick.
她本来可以成为一名著名的艺术家的 但是她生了病
I'm glad my mom never gets sick.
我很庆幸我妈妈从来没生过病
I don't know what I'd do without her.
要是没有她我都不知道该怎么办好
Aoise, come back here. You're supposed to be modeling for me.
阿洛伊斯 快回来 你不是给我当模特的吗
Well, models are supposed to get paid,you know.
可是 模特是要讲报酬的 对吧
Not if they don't sit still.
要是乱动的话就没有啦
Aloise, sit...
阿洛伊斯 坐...
Thank you, William. It's wonderful.
真谢谢你 威廉大叔 这太棒了
Such soft leather.
这皮多软啊
- Where did you get it? - Where'd you get it, William?
-你从哪里弄到的啊? -这块皮革是从哪里来的啊 威廉大叔
- Your apron! - Oh, no!
-你的围裙! -噢 不!
Look at your faces!What have you been doing?
看看你们的小脏脸儿! 你们都干什么去了?
Your father will blame me for sure.
你爸爸肯定要怪我了
Aloise, your mother's been looking for you.
阿洛伊斯 你妈妈正找你呢
Coming, Papa.
就来 爸爸
Look at you.Who's been painting your face?
瞧瞧你 谁把你画成了大花脸啊?
- Hello, Master Cogez. - Nello, William.
-你好 库格兹先生 -尼洛 威廉
- Say, "Bye-bye, Nello. " -Bye-bye, Nello.
-说 "再见 尼洛" -再见 尼洛
- Say, "Bye-bye, William. " - Bye-bye, William.
-说 "再见 威廉叔叔" -再见 威廉叔叔
- Bye-bye - Bye, Aloise
-再见 -再见 阿洛伊斯
Oh, look at you.
瞧瞧你
Lucky man, Baas Cogez, huh?
巴斯·库格兹真是个幸运的人 对吧?
Oh look, you and Patrasche get that milk to town before you lose your customers.
你和帕奇快点送牛奶到镇子上去 不然人家下次就不订你的牛奶了
Clean your face on the way.
在路上记得把脸洗干净
- Thank you, William. - All right.
-谢谢你 威廉大叔 -没事的 去吧
- Children! Children! Sit down. - Hi, Aloise.
-孩子们!孩子们! 坐下 -嗨 阿洛伊斯
There's a great painting inside that cathedral.
在那个大教堂有一幅很棒的画
Grandpa says Mother once saw it.
爷爷说妈妈曾经见过它
Wish I could see it too.
我也想去看看
Are you an admirer of Rubens as well?
你也很崇拜鲁本斯吗?
Yes, sir. He's my hero.
是的 先生 他是我的英雄
I'm sure the great master is happy to see bright new eyes looking up at him.
我肯定这位大师 看到有这样一双年轻明亮的眼睛注视着他会很开心的
I want to meet him.
我想见见他
Rubens passed away many years ago.
鲁本斯许多年前就去世了
Of course, his art lives on.
当然 他的艺术还流传在世间
Great men and their deeds always do live on.
伟人和他们的事迹总会流芳百世的
And that's a comfort.
而这也算是一种告慰吧
Please, sir.
请等一下先生
Tell me more. I want to become a great artist too.
能不能再跟我说说 我也想成为一个伟大的艺术家
Oh, you do?
噢 真的吗?
Well, you've made a proper start.
好吧 你开了个好头
Rubens was a master of every aspect of art.
鲁本斯在艺术的各个方面都是大师级别的存在
Composition, light
构图 光线
movement.
动作
But he had to study.He studied down there, around the corner.
但是他也得学习 就在那里 街道转角的附近
- Right here in this city? - He was a great teacher as well.
-就在这座城里吗? -他也曾是个伟大的老师
But what made him really great was that he was interested...
但是真正让他变得伟大的
was interested and excited about everything.
是他对任何事情都充满着兴趣与激情
I'm like that.
我就是这样的
I'm sure you are.
我也相信你一定是的
Michel!
米歇尔!
Milk?
牛奶?
Artists of our caliber should only drink cognac.
我们这种级别的艺术家应该喝的是白兰地吧
Let's see what these characters are up to, shall we?
我们去会会那些人吧 怎么样?
Robert Kessler
罗伯特·凯斯勒
may I present Master Michel La Grande.
请允许我向你介绍米歇尔·拉格兰德大师
I've studied your painting in the town hall, sir.
我在市政厅学习过您的画作 先生
I believe you know his father,our esteemed mayor.
我想你一定认识他的父亲 也就是我们敬爱的市长
Of course.
当然
Robert's been studying in London's Royal Conservatory of Art.
罗伯特最近在伦敦皇家音乐学院学习艺术
As you can see, he has a lot of potential.
如你所见 他很有潜能
You always had an eye for potential.
你总是有一双慧眼
-Let me introduce you to my friend...Nello
-让我来介绍一下我的朋友...尼洛
Master Steerns. Robert.
这位是斯蒂恩斯大师 这是罗伯特
That's right I don't suppose I know his father.Do I?
我想我应该不认识他的父亲吧 对吗
Dietrich, please.
迪特里克 请注意你的身份
Yes, well...
哦 好...
I was prepared to show Robert Rubens'greatest work, if you care to join us.
我准备带罗伯特看看鲁本斯最伟大的画作 不介意的话就一起吧
I was just on my way,with my friend, Nello.
我和我的朋友尼洛马上就来
Can Patrasche come too?
帕奇也能一起进去吗?
The priest doesn't allow dogs.
那些牧师们是不会让狗进入的
He barely tolerates humans unless they have...
他们也就只能容忍一些...
potential.
有潜力的人
- So tie up your friend and then join us. - Okay.
-把你的朋友安置好然后和我们一起进去吧 -好的
Come, Patrasche.
过来 帕奇
Michel, I'm starting a little salon on Tuesdays.
米歇尔 星期二我会办一个展览
You should drop by for schnapps.
你真的应该过来喝一杯
I'm afraid I'll be busy for the next...
我想我最近...
four or five years.
四五年内都会很忙
That, my boy, is what we call a brushoff.
我的孩子 这就是我们所说的拒绝
Not at all. I'm going off to Rome to paint some murals.
不 不是的 我要去罗马画壁画
A new commission from the Church.
教堂指派的新任务
Really?
真的吗?
Does his Holiness pay well?
教皇陛下舍得给钱吗?
I myself would pay to paint in the city of Michelangelo.
能在米开朗基罗的城市里作画 倒贴钱我都愿意
Well, to each his own.
也对 人各有志
This is the painting here, behind the drape.
这就是那幅画 就在帘子后面
Now, where's the priest?
牧师们呢?
Father! We've come to see the Rubens.
神父!我们来看鲁本斯的画作啦!
Does light hurt the painting?
光线会伤到这幅画吗?
On the contrary, young Robert.
恰恰相反 罗伯特
It's light that brings a painting to life.
正是光线给这幅画注入了生命
So why does he keep it covered?
那为什么要把它遮住呢?
Let's just say, it wasn't Rubens' idea.
这并不是鲁本斯的本意
His paintings were meant to be enjoyed by everyone.
他的画作本来是应该让人人都有机会欣赏的
As if the masses were interested in art.
说的就好像人人都对艺术感兴趣一样
Father.
神父
Oh, yes
噢 对了
Robert, you surely have a silver franc.
罗伯特 你应该有个银法郎吧
Bless you.
保佑你
This is the house of God!
这里可是圣殿!
- Patrasche, no! Come! - You!
-帕奇 别这样!过来! -你!
- You thief! Thief! - Nello.
-你这个小偷! 你这个贼! -尼洛
Little sinner!
你这罪人!
If you worried so much about souls as you do silver...
你要是像关心法郎一样关心苍生...
there'd be no sinners in this city!
就天下无贼了!
Nello, it's all right!
尼洛 没事了!
Patrasche, I was going to see Rubens' greatest painting.
帕奇 我本来能看到鲁本斯最伟大的画作的
You found my darling dog.
你找到我亲爱的小狗了
Your dog? I found him by the side of the road. He was almost dead.
你的狗? 我是在路边发现他的 他当时都快死了
Either way, he is mine.
谁管你怎么发现的 他是我的
He doesn't like you.
可他不喜欢你
As long as he obeys me, boy.
我只要他听我的命令 小子
Now, one way or another...
现在 不管怎样...
I am taking my animal back.
我要把这畜生带回去
Understand me, boy?
懂了吗 小子?
You understand me?!
还不快给我?!
Run, Patrasche, run!
快跑帕奇 快跑!
- You try to run from me? - Stop!
-想从我手掌心里溜走? -住手!
- I'll teach you better than that! - No!
-看我不打死你! -不要!
This dog is mine!
这狗是我的
It's my dog.
我的狗!
You stole him from me!
是你从我这里偷的!
Now, get away or I'll cut your damn heart out!
现在 给我滚开 不然老子就把你的心挖出来!
No, Patrasche is mine! You left him to die!
不 帕奇是我的! 你当时把他打得半死就丢下了它!
You let that dog be! Leave him alone!Get behind me! Get back behind me!
住手! 离开那条狗! 快到我身后来 我来保护你!
You want trouble, peddler? You've got it!
你想惹麻烦吗 臭贩子? 你死定了!
Come on!
来啊!
Are you insane?!
你疯了吗?
Nello, are you all right?
尼洛 你还好吗?
Look out!
小心!
It's over.
没事了
It's done.
都结束了
Nello, come with me.
尼洛 跟我来
You're a brave dog, Patrasche.
你真是条勇敢的狗 帕奇
When can I take my bandage off?
我什么时候能把我的绷带拆下来?
树 屋
字 幕 组
电 影 组
Keep it on for a while. Keeps the dirt from the cut.
你还是多带一会儿吧 保持创口的洁净
Are you a great artist, sir?
你是一个伟大的艺术家吗 先生?
郑重声明:本作品之片源、字幕均来自互联网 版权归原电影公司所有任何组织和个人不得公开传播或用于任何商业盈利用途 否则一切后果由该组织或个人承担！本字幕组和制作者不承担任何法律及连带责任！请自觉于下载后24小时内删除如果喜欢本片 请购买正版！
I strive to be, Nello.
我正为此而奋斗呢 尼洛
But perhaps not.
但也许终其一生也达不到
I think you're great, sir.
我觉得你很伟大 先生
I thank you.
谢谢你
- But Rubens was the best, though, right? - Rubens was a genius.
-尽管鲁本斯还是最棒的 对吗? -鲁本斯是个天才
- Is that greater than great? - Genius is a greatness...
-意思是比伟大更伟大吗? -天才就是...
that burns like an eternal flame.
燃烧并绽放出永恒光焰的伟大
That's you. I like that one.
这是你的肖像 我喜欢这个
You have good taste.
你的品味不错啊
A very gifted student drew that for me.
这是一个非常有天赋的学生为我画的
Did he become great?
他有变得伟大吗?
She could've been.
她本来是可以的
But as you know, Nello...
但是你知道的 尼洛...
in our society, no one lets you forget what station you're from.
在我们的社会里 总有人提醒你你的身份地位
Especially for a woman.
尤其对一个女人来说
She was from a poor family.
她出身贫寒
She was young.
当时她还年轻
I was foolish.
我真蠢
I let her get away.
我就那样让她离开了
- Master La Grande? -Yes?
-拉格兰德先生? -怎么了?
I have a friend, Aloise.
我有一个好朋友 她叫阿洛伊斯
She models for me.
她给我当模特
- Would you like to see her picture? - Of course.
-你想看看我给她画的画吗? -当然
- You drew this? - Is it any good?
-是你画的? -画得还行吗?
It's exceptional.
画得非常漂亮
Especially for a boy your age.
尤其是对于你这么大的男孩子来说
Perspective is off here and there, but that comes with study.
这些地方还需要一些透视效果 但这需要学习
Do you ever give lessons in exchange for work?
我帮您干活 您能教我画画吗?
I'd be so honored, but I'm off to Rome.
我很乐意 但我马上要去罗马
What about your friend? Does she give lessons?
那您的朋友呢? 她教课吗?
She went away. I never saw her again.
她走了 我再没见到过她
But, anyway, you don't need lessons right now.
但是现在你暂时还不需要上课
The main thing is to keep drawing from your heart the way you do.
现在最重要的是你坚持用心画下去 按你自己的方式
and examine, look at things.
要去仔细观察事物
The greater part of drawing comes before you even touch the paper.
绘画最重要的部分 是在你接触画纸之前
Ask questions, find out what things are made of.
探究疑问 找出事物是如何构成的
Store information for the inner eye, the eye of the intuition.
为内心的眼睛 直觉的眼睛去积累素材
Is that how Rubens did it? I want to become like him.
鲁本斯就是这样的吗? 我想像他一样
That's good. Always reach for the stars.
很好 要尽力去达到更高的目标
You could be great, Nello. Why not?
你会成功的 尼洛 为什么不呢?
Do you believe you could be great?
你相信自己会成功吗?
Maybe.
也许吧
Good.
很好
Slow down!
停下来!
I don't believe this.
真难以置信
Aloise, we talked about you racing through the fields.
阿洛伊斯 我们已经谈过不许你去田里骑马的事了
Besides there's work to be done.
而且我们还有活儿要干
Nello says when he's a great artist, I'll never have to push a cart again.
尼洛说等他成了大画家 我就再也不用推手推车了
Down you get.
下来
Well, Most artists would be happy to settle for enough to eat.
很多画家只要能吃饱就满足了
Did he tell you that too,uh?
他没告诉你这个吧?
Peter Paul Rubens was great and rich. Nello knows all about him.
彼得·保罗·鲁本斯就很伟大而且富有 尼洛很了解他
Nello can't even read or write.
尼洛甚至不识字
So I'll teach him, and he'll use me as his model to paint.
所以我要教他认字 他会让我当他的模特
He's such a good artist, Papa.
他是个很不错的画家 爸爸
I don't want Nello filling your mind with any more nonsense.
我不想尼洛再给你讲那些胡话
And there's no more riding. You've got work to do.
不许再骑马了 你有活儿要干
Nello have to find another model.
尼洛得再找个模特了
Come on.
过来
Your father just wants what's best. All fathers do.
你父亲只希望你好好的 天下所有父亲都是这样
- Why doesn't he like Nello? - He likes Nello.
-他为什么不喜欢尼洛? -他当然喜欢尼洛
He just remembers what it was like when he was poor.
他只是忘不了那段穷苦日子
How hard life can be.
那时生活有多艰难
Money doesn't make people happy.
可钱不一定能使人幸福
Nello and his grandfather, they're poor and they're happy.
尼洛和他爷爷 他们很穷 但是他们很幸福
You are so smart.
你真聪明
I don't know who you take after.
我都不知道你像谁了
Nello will be great. I know he will.
尼洛会成功的 我相信他
Of course he will. He has you to believe in him.
有你这么相信他 他当然会成功
Nello? Is that you?
尼洛? 是你吗?
Master La Grande.
拉格兰德先生
You're home.
您回来了
- Yes and no. I must return to Rome. - Oh
-是 也不是 我还要回罗马 -哦
But not for long. The bishop wants a smaller nose, that's all.
但不会去很久 主教想让鼻子画得小一点儿 就这样
But look at you. I barely recognized you.
但是看看你 我甚至都没认出你
Of course, I recognized your friend, Patrasche.
当然 我认得你的朋友 帕奇
And your model hasn't changed a bit. Master Rubens.
而且你的偶像可一点儿也没变 鲁本斯大师
But let's see.
让我看看
Let's see how you are doing.
看看你画得怎么样
Your eye has grown clear and your hand strong.
你的眼光更敏锐 手法更强了
You've cared wisely for your talent.
你很明智地发挥了你的天才
Perhaps it's time to graduate to painting.
也许是时候升级到油画了
Painting?
油画?
Perhaps it's time.
也许是时候了
This is for you as well. All prepared.
这些也是给你的 都准备好了
And the brushes.
还有这些画笔
You'll need many brushes.
你需要很多画笔
Those are all for me?
这些都是给我的吗?
Tools of the trade for a fellow artist.
这些工具能换来一位画家
Early Christmas present.
提前的圣诞礼物
I've never seen so many beautiful things before.
我从没见过这么多漂亮的东西
Those pigments are very strong. Here...
这些颜料色泽非常浓 看这个...
try one color at a time.
一次试一种颜色
Place it next to other colors...
把它放在别的颜色旁边
mix them, fall in love with the colors.
将它们混合 爱上这些颜色
And then look at nature...
然后观察大自然...
and your surroundings.
和你周围的景物
See how these colors are reflected.
看看这些颜色是怎样的
How many colors, for instance, in your blouse?
比如 你的上衣 有几种颜色?
Let's see. Blue, of course.
我们来看看 有蓝色 肯定的
There's white.
还有白色
But it has other colors as well.
但它也有其它的颜色
But, also, green will bring it to that shade exactly.
但是 一点点绿色能让颜色看起来更接近
Experiment.
这只是个试验
Here.
拿着这个
Sometimes at the end of a day I have 30 colors...
有时候一天下来 我的调色板上会有30种颜色...
in my palette, different shades.
明暗各不相同
Now for a box for you.
现在我要送你一个盒子
- Nello. Nello? - What?
-尼洛 尼洛? -怎么了?
The city fathers...
市里的神父们...
sponsor a Rubens Junior Art Contest each Christmas.
每个圣诞节会主办一个鲁本斯初级绘画比赛
You must enter it.
你必须参加
I could never win.
我赢不了的
What's that?
你说什么?
Is that my pupil speaking?Um?
这是我的学生说的话吗?嗯?
How could I?
我怎么能赢呢?
The first step to winning is believing you could win.
成功的第一步 就是相信你能赢
Of course you can win, Nello.
你当然能赢 尼洛
It's too late for me.
已经太晚了
There's plenty of time before Christmas. You can do it.
在圣诞之前你还有很多时间 你能行的
I mean it's too late for me to start my art studies.
我的意思是开始学画画已经太迟了
Nonsense.
胡说
Rubens himself was older than you when he started.
鲁本斯开始学画画的时候年龄比你还大
- Really? - Really.
-真的? -真的
And did I forget to mention...
我忘了告诉你...
that the winner gets 1000 silver francs...
胜者能拿到1000法郎奖金...
and a scholarship to art school?
还能拿到去艺术院校的奖学金
Did you hear that, Patrasche?
听见了吗 帕奇?
One thousand silver francs.
一千法郎
And he's going to win it, Patrasche. He's going to win it.
他会赢的 帕奇 他会赢的
-Hi Aloise. - Hi, Nello. I made you some cookies.
-嗨 阿洛伊斯 -嗨 尼洛 我给你做了点饼干
They're not that good, though. Mother says I ride better than I cook.
做得不太好 妈妈说我骑马比做饼干强
Papa thought the heart-shaped cookie was for him.
爸爸以为心形的饼干是给他的呢
And this one's for Patrasche.
这个是给帕奇的
Thanks, but...
谢谢你 但是...
they're too pretty to eat.
它们太漂亮了 我都舍不得吃了
I've got something for you too.
我也有东西要给你
It's beautiful.
太美了
- What is it? - It's what it will be that matters.
-这是什么? -重要的是它将是什么
I'll call it Portrait of a Princess.
我把它叫做公主的画像
It's beautiful.
太漂亮了
I feel so small when I look up at the sky.
当我看着天空的时候 我觉得自己是那么渺小
Really?
真的?
Why are some people born rich, some poor...
为什么有些人生来就富有 有些却生来就贫穷...
some healthy...
有些人健康...
some real sick?
有些人却带着疾病?
It just isn't fair.
这不公平
I really hadn't thought much about that yet.
我还没想过这些
Ever since my mother died...
妈妈去世以后...
I've wondered where she went.
我一直在想她去了哪里
Maybe she's one of those real bright stars that come out every night.
也许她是夜空中那些闪耀着的明星中的一颗
I hope so.
希望是这样
It wouldn't be right if the spirit of a great man like Rubens...
如果像鲁本斯那样的伟人
and good people like my mother just didn't go on after they died.
和我妈妈那样的好人死后没有灵魂的话... 那多遗憾啊
I'm sure you're right, Nello.
我相信你是对的 尼洛
God's too smart for that.
上帝对此很清楚
- I'd better go. - It's time to go, Aloise.
-我该走了 -该走了 阿洛伊斯
Meet me here tomorrow night, and I'll finish your sketch.
明天晚上在这儿见 我把你的画画完
All right, Nello.
好的 尼洛
You're going to be a great artist, just like Rubens.
你一定会成为一个伟大的画家 就像鲁本斯一样
Listen.
听
Can you hear it?
你听见了吗?
Yes.
听见了
Music.
有音乐
It's the circus.
是马戏团的人
I saw them pass earlier on the way to the city.
我之前看见他们在去城里的路上
Papa says circus people stuff little girls in sacks and sell them.
爸爸说马戏团的人把小女孩装在麻袋里卖掉
Like grain? That's silly.
像卖粮食一样? 怎么可能
They travel and play games and make people happy.
他们四处旅行 表演马戏 让人们开心的
How could they be bad?
他们怎么能是坏人呢?
I don't know.
我不知道
I better get you home first.
我最好先把你送回家
Nello Daas, if you're not afraid, I'm not afraid.
尼洛·达斯 如果你不害怕 我就不害怕
Maybe we should go back.
也许我们应该回去
Are you kidding? This is great.
你在开玩笑吗? 这太好玩了
Come on, Nello.
来吧 尼洛
You will be great one day, little one.
有一天你会成为伟大的人 孩子
Your life and love will touch many.
你俩的生命和爱情会感动很多人
Your stars are crossed.
你们的星相相交
Your hearts beat as one.
你们的心跳相合
You have known each other before.
你们前生就认识了
In this life, you will finally find true happiness.
这一生 你们最终会找到真正的幸福
Aloise! Where are you? Can you hear me?
阿洛伊斯! 你在哪儿? 听见我了吗?
Aloise! Answer me!
阿洛伊斯! 回答我!
- Oh, my God! Thank God you're all right. - I'm sorry, Papa. I fell asleep.
-哦 上帝! 感谢上帝你没事 -对不起 爸爸 我睡着了
Master Cogez, it was all my fault. I wanted to draw her picture.
库格兹先生 都是我的错 我想给她画画
Do you have any idea how worried we've been? Any idea at all?
你知道我们有多担心吗? 你知道吗?
- Papa, no. It was my fault. - I'll deal with you later.
-爸爸 不 这都是我的错 -我回去再教训你
You're thoughtless and irresponsible, Nello.
你太轻率了 而且不负责任 尼洛
Aloise is our life. I won't let you jeopardize that.
阿洛伊斯是我们的命 我不会让你伤害她
Do you understand me?
明白吗?
Millie, take Aloise inside, please.
米莉 带阿洛伊斯进去
Nello, would you come here?
尼洛 你能过来一下吗?
That picture you did of Aloise.
你画的阿洛伊斯的画像
Personally I think the painting is foolish,
我个人认为那幅画糟透了
but it does look like her, and my wife seems likes it.
但看起来确实很像她 我妻子很喜欢
I'll buy it from you.
我买了
It's not for sale.
那幅画不卖
So be it.
那好吧
- Anna. Fetch the boy's picture. - Master Cogez.
-安娜 把他的画拿来 -库格兹先生
It's a present.
那是我送给阿洛伊斯的礼物
Nello, I want you to stay away from my daughter.
尼洛 我要你离我女儿远点儿
- But Aloise is my friend. - You're not welcome here anymore.
-但阿洛伊斯是我的朋友 -这里不欢迎你了
Because of last night?
因为昨晚吗?
No.
不
Because it's for the best.
因为这样最好
Best for who, sir?
为了谁好 先生?
I could've seen the Rubens with that silver franc.
有了那枚银币我就能看到鲁本斯的画
I couldn't sell her picture.
但我不能卖那幅画
One day when we're great, Patrasche...
等有一天我们成功了 帕奇
Aloise's drawing will be worth its weight in silver.
阿洛伊斯的那副肖像就会一纸千金
Don't cry. I'll talk to him.
别哭了 我会跟你爸爸谈谈
You're right to be upset with them, but you've gone too far.
你生他们的气我可以理解 但你过分了
She'll get over it.
她会好的
- Nello's like a brother to her. - Brother? Anna, come on!
-尼洛就像她的兄长 -兄长? 安娜 算了吧!
- You know where this is going. - What if it did come to pass
-你知道事情会怎么发展 -就算是这样
would that be so terrible? Nello is a fine, hardworking boy...
有这么可怕吗? 尼洛是个很不错的 勤奋的男孩...
He's an orphan.
他是个孤儿
No girl can do better than to be happy.
没有女孩不想幸福的
Even if it means marrying a tinker's son, like you were.
即使是嫁给一个修补匠的儿子 就像你过去那样
I married you for love. I went against my father's wishes.
我因为爱你才嫁给你 违抗我父亲的意愿
And I didn't judge you because you were poor and had dreams.
我并没有因为你贫穷得只剩梦想而嫌弃你
No, no. I had ambitions. This boy dreams of being an artist.
不 不是的 我有雄心壮志 可这孩子只想成为一个画家
What kind of future is that?
那有什么前途?
I turned your father's simple farm into a prosperous mill.
我把你父亲简陋的农场变成了一个兴旺的磨坊
Is it so wrong for a father to want more for his daughter?
一个父亲 想给他的女儿更好的 难道错了吗?
No.
不是
But this mill will provide for Aloise, always.
但是这间磨坊会养活阿洛伊斯 一直会的
You forget. I know what it's like to be poor.
你忘了 我知道穷苦日子是什么样儿
Nello.
尼洛
It's Aloise's birthday soon.
阿洛伊斯的生日快到了
I made her something.
我给她做了件东西
I'm not going this year.
今年我不去了
Master Cogez is a strong man...
库格兹先生是个很强势的人...
but you know there is good there.
但是你该明白他也是个好人
He just wants the best for Aloise.
他只是希望她女儿能过得好
Master Cogez thinks that money is all that's important.
库格兹先生认为有钱才是最重要的
Poor, my boy.
可怜啊 我的孩子
Being poor is hard on you.
贫穷让你过得很艰难
We've lots. We've Patrasche and each other.
可我们拥有很多东西 我们有帕奇 还有彼此
I don't care what he thinks.
我不在乎库格兹怎么想
A little more food would not be disagreeable, though, would it?
不过多一点吃的会更好吧 不是吗?
One day we will all be with God and realize this was just a dream.
总有一天 我们都会回到上帝那里 然后意识到这一切只是一个梦
Just one big dream.
一个很长很宏大的梦
Sometimes good, sometimes bad.
有时候好 有时候坏
Will we really all be together again after we die?
我们死后真的还会在一起吗?
Of course!
当然!
Our real home is with God.
我们真正的家 是在上帝那里
And he will not be happy until we all come back to him.
而且直到我们都回到他那儿 上帝才会高兴
- Then I will see Mother again? - Oh, yes, yes.
-那我还能再见到妈妈吗? -能 当然能
But remember:
但要记住:
She's here now.
她现在就在这里
Always with you, even though you can't see her.
即使你看不到她 她也一直在你身边
Here she is, the birthday girl.
她来了 寿星小丫头
Thank you for the lovely gift for Aloise.
谢谢你送阿洛伊斯的礼物
And so then I threw the old fool out...
然后我把那个愚蠢的老家伙扔了出去...
and then I bought her house for nothing.
然后没出钱就得到了她的房子
- Sir? - Thank you, Millie.
-先生? -谢谢你 米莉
Thank you.
谢谢
You look very beautiful tonight, Millie.
米莉 你今晚看起来真美
Olga, thank you very much for coming.
奥尔加 谢谢你今晚能来
Sweetheart, you go on ahead. I have business I want to discuss with Nicholas.
亲爱的 你先走吧 我有事情要和尼古拉斯谈谈
Business tonight? Discuss something tonight?
谈事情? 今晚要谈事情?
I won't have my wits about me. Not after this much ale.
今晚我可没什么脑子 尤其是喝了这么多酒之后
Exactly, my friend! Exactly.
当然要谈 我的朋友! 当然
Because you are too sly for me when you are sober.
因为对我来说你清醒的时候太滑头了
You've had enough.
够了 你喝多了
I know when I have had enough.
我知道自己什么时候才算喝多
Don't you ever tell me how to do my business, woman!
还轮不到你来告诉我该怎么做 娘儿们!
Now you go on home.
现在你给我回家
Aloise! Aloise!
阿洛伊斯!
Happy birthday, Aloise.
生日快乐 阿洛伊斯
Nello!
尼洛!
How pretty. I love it.
真漂亮 我喜欢
- It's hard not seeing you anymore. - I know. For me too.
-见不到你真难熬 -我知道 我也是
After the art contest, everything will be different.
等美术大赛结束之后 一切就会不同了
I pray every night for God to let you win.
我每晚都向上帝祈祷让你赢得比赛
Then I can't lose, Aloise.
那我就不会输 阿洛伊斯
Fire!
着火啦!
Oh, dear God!
哦 上帝啊!
我的天啊!
The house and the barn could go next!
过一会儿房子和马厩也会烧着的!
Everybody get in a line!
大家站成一队!
Get to the stream! Get the buckets!
去溪边! 拿桶来!
Millie, get the buckets! Get the buckets!
米莉 快去拿桶! 快去!
- Help! - I'm trying!
-帮帮忙! -我正在努力!
Grandfather!
爷爷!
What are you doing?
你在做什么?
These old bones can still help a neighbor.
这把老骨头还能给邻居帮点忙
Someone!
来人!
快来个人!
- I'm going to lose everything! - Someone!
-我就要一无所有了! -快来人啊!
Stephens! Get on the pump!
斯蒂芬斯 快去压水泵!
More!
再来!
再来点!
- Water? - Yes.
-要喝点水吗? -好的
Thank you, William.
谢谢你 威廉
I owe you, William. Without your help, we'd have lost the barn too.
我欠你的 威廉 如果没有你 马厩也保不住
Are you all right, Grandfather?
你还好吗 爷爷?
A little winded.
有点气喘
Don't you find it mysterious?
你不觉得奇怪吗?
I looked. I found no broken lantern.
我看过了 没有找到任何坏掉的油灯
树 屋
字 幕 组
电 影 组
How could fresh, stored grain burst into flames all by itself?
刚储存起来的粮食怎么会自己着起火来呢?
You mean someone started the fire deliberately?
你是说有人蓄意纵火?
郑重声明:本作品之片源、字幕均来自互联网 版权归原电影公司所有任何组织和个人不得公开传播或用于任何商业盈利用途 否则一切后果由该组织或个人承担！本字幕组和制作者不承担任何法律及连带责任！请自觉于下载后24小时内删除如果喜欢本片 请购买正版！
Does anybody have any idea who may have visited here after Aloise's party?
有人知道阿洛伊斯的生日宴会之后 有谁来过这里吗?
You always see the worst in things. Accidents happen.
你总是把事情看得那么坏 意外总是有的
This was no accident.
这不是意外
Come here, boy.
过来 孩子
Come here!
过来!
You were looking for revenge, weren't you, boy?
你是在报复 对吗 小子?
For Master Cogez not allowing you to see Aloise.
因为库格兹先生不让你见阿洛伊斯
Was Nello here last night?
尼洛昨晚来过吗?
What are you holding?
你手里是什么?
Where did you get that?
你从哪儿得来的?
Anna, where did she get that?
安娜 她从哪儿拿的?
Did you see my daughter last night?
昨晚你见我的女儿了吗?
I don't believe this. Are you responsible for this fire?
简直难以置信 是你放的火?
Do you really think that Nello could do such a thing?
你觉得尼洛会做这种事吗?
People will go to any lengths for revenge.
人为了报仇可以不择手段
I was in bed when the fire started!
着火的时候 我正睡在床上
- You started the fire. - Nello could never have done such a thing.
-就是你放的火 -尼洛绝不会做这样的事
Wait a minute, Anna. Stephens is right.
等等 安娜 斯蒂芬斯说得对
The boy started the fire because he was angry with me.
就是他放的火 因为他恨我
- I did not! - You're a liar! Nello Daas
-我没有! -你这个骗子! 尼洛·达斯
On what grounds do you attack my grandson?
你有什么证据指责他?
A birthday present?
一个生日礼物?
I brought the puppet, but that was all.
我拿了木偶送给阿洛伊斯 但仅此而已
Proof! There you have it! There is your proof.
证据! 就是它! 这就是证据!
But I didn't do it! I didn't start that fire!
但我没有那么做! 我没有放火!
Please believe me!
请相信我!
Nello!
尼洛!
No one will do business with me.
没人要买我的牛奶
I know, lad.
我知道 小伙子
Stephens' man was already here.He's taken over your milk run.
斯蒂芬斯的人已经来过了 他已经接手你送牛奶的活儿了
So that's who's been doing my deliveries.
原来是他抢了我的生意
Listen, Nello, I have some chairs. You and Patrasche can deliver them for me.
听着 尼洛 这有些椅子 你和帕奇帮我送一下吧
I'll give you money. Let's get rid of your cans. You can leave them here.
我会给你钱的 拿下来这些罐子 你可以把它们放我这儿
Why don't you ask Stephens' helper?
你为什么不找斯蒂芬斯的帮手
Well...
这...
since I decided to quit drinking milk this morning...
自从我今天早晨把牛奶戒掉之后...
Stephens and I aren't on speaking terms.
斯蒂芬斯和我连泛泛之交都算不上了
Of course, we were never very close.
当然 我们也从没未亲近过
Come on.
来吧
Rosa!
罗莎!
After your mother died, a part of your grandfather died too.
在你母亲去世之后 你祖父的一部分生命也跟着枯萎了
And some of me.
我也一样
Your mother was a very special person.
你的母亲是一个非常特别的人
What was she like?
她是什么样的人
Always smiling.
她总是面带微笑
A hard life. Devil knows what she had to smile about, but...
生活艰辛 天知道她在笑什么 但是...
oh, she could light up a room.
她却能照亮一整个房间
I wish I could have known her.
我真希望我能了解她
If you know yourself, you know her.
只要你了解你自己 你就了解她了
When I win the art contest...
等我赢了美术大赛...
everybody will know Nello Daas...
所有人都将知道尼洛·达斯...
son of Mary...
玛丽的儿子...
grandson of Jehan.
约翰的孙子
- Everyone. - Everyone.
-所有人都会 -对 所有人
Grandpa left this to me.
祖父留下了这个给我
It's from your mother.
是你母亲写的信
"Dearest Father:
最最亲爱的父亲
How long I've wanted to write you but could not find the words.
长久以来一直想给您写信却始终找不到恰当的言语
I had to leave. "
我必须要离开
I hope you'll understand.
我希望您能理解我
I did not want to hurt you or cause anyone disgrace.
我并不想伤害您或招致别人的羞辱
God has his reasons, of that I am sure.
我相信 上帝自有他的理由
The birth of my son was the most joyful day of my life.
我的儿子出生那天是我生命中最快乐的一天
It proves to me that real happiness comes not from our possessions
它向我证明了真正的幸福不是来自于财富
or our positions, but from within.
或者地位 而是源于我们的内心
Father, I so look forward to sitting with you again by the water...
父亲 我是多么想和您再次坐在水边...
watching the boats pass, with your beautiful grandson on your lap.
将您漂亮的孙子放在您的腿上 看船只驶过
I heard Anna had a daughter named Aloise.
我听说安娜有个女儿 叫阿洛伊斯
Please give them my love.
请转达我对他们爱
"Did Nicholas Cogez start building his windmill?
"尼古拉斯·库格兹开始建造他的风车了么?
Well, for now I must go.
好啦 现在我必须走了
Give everyone my very best wishes for a happy, healthy Christmas.
祝每个人都有一个健康快乐的圣诞节
Love always, your daughter, Mary.
永远爱你的女儿 玛丽
P.S. His name is Nello. "
附注 他的名字叫尼洛"
Why not come back to the shop and have a bite?
回商店吃点东西怎么样?
You could stay the night.
你可以留下来过夜
I could use the company.
我有这个权利做主
Thank you...
谢谢你...
but I've something very important to do.
但我有非常重要的事情要去做
Please, sir! Here's my painting for the Rubens Art Contest.
你好 先生!这是我参加鲁本斯美术比赛的作品
I'm sorry, the deadline passed three minutes ago.
非常抱歉 可是截止时间在三分钟前就到了
No, but I must win.
不 我一定要赢
Perhaps next year.
等明年吧
I have to win this year! It's my only hope.
我今年一定要赢!这是我唯一的希望
I'm sorry. I'm late and my family is waiting.
非常抱歉 我马上就要迟到了而且我的家人正在等我
Please, sir.
求求你了 先生
This is...
这...
very good.
很漂亮
This is...
这画...
really good.
棒极了
I'll take it.
我会交上去的
Thank you, sir.
太感谢了 先生
- Merry Christmas. - Merry Christmas to you, sir.
-圣诞快乐 -圣诞快乐 先生
Good luck.
祝你好运
You're late again on the rent, boy.
你又没有按时交租金 小子
How many times have I warned you?
我警告过你多少次了?
I still have to pay off Grandfather's funeral.
我得先付清爷爷的葬礼费用
I am not interested in your troubles.
我对你的问题不感兴趣
You will have to leave.
你必须得滚出去了
As for this month's, I'll settle for the dog.
至于这个月的租金 就用这只狗来抵账
No! He's my best friend.
不!他是我最好的朋友
You can't afford to feed yourself.
你连自己都养不活
When I win the art contest, we'll have all the money we need.
等我赢了比赛 我就会有足够的钱了
You are a dreamer, boy. Just like your mother.
孩子 你跟你妈一样 只会做白日梦
My mother was a great woman.
我的母亲是个伟大的女人
Keep the dog. I'll take this.
留着你的狗吧 我把这拿走了
No!
不!
And you leave me every miserable scrap that you own.
把你这儿的东西都给我留下
I want you out of here by the morning.
我希望你在明早之前滚出这里
- But I've no place to go, sir. - You are not my responsibility!
-但我没有地方可去 先生 -这不关我的事!
Don't blame me for your miserable life, boy.Blame your mother.
不要把你的悲惨的生活赖到我身上 要怨就怨你的母亲
Out of here by the morning.
明早之前滚出去
Can't you wait until after Christmasto rebuild?
为什么不等过了圣诞节再重建?
I tell you why.
我告诉你为什么
Because with what we lost in the fire,I have to work the mill twice as much.
因为大火带来的损失 我必须让磨坊加倍工作
Besides, I have nowhere to store the grain.
而且 粮食没有存放的地方了
I should never have let you borrow on the farm to build that damn windmill.
我真不该让你借钱去在农场建那该死的风车
Really? Well, you like your city-bought party dresses well enough.
是吗? 你不是很喜欢城里卖的礼服裙吗
I liked our simple life.
我喜欢我们简单的生活
I liked the man I married.
我爱的是我嫁给的那个男人
You've become just like Stephens,driven by the money instead of your heart.
你已经变得像斯蒂芬斯一样 被金钱所奴役而丧失了自我
My duty is to provide for my family.
我的责任是养活我的家人
It takes more than money to provide for your family, Nicholas.
可是家人需要的是比金钱更重要的东西 尼古拉斯
Welcome, ladies and gentlemen.
女士们 先生们 欢迎大家
Every Christmas, nothing gives me more pleasure...
每一个圣诞节 没有任何事情...
Well, let's say, almost nothing...
应该说是 几乎没有任何事情
than the Peter Paul Rubens Young People's Art Competition.
比彼得·保罗·鲁本斯青年美术大赛更能带给我快乐
For without Rubens, what would our city be?
要是没有鲁本斯我们的城市会是什么样子?
It would be like a Christmas without...
就如同圣诞节没有
...roasted pheasant, plum pudding,fine wine.
烤鸡 葡萄干布丁 美酒
Cold ale! Hail ale!
冰啤酒! 啤酒万岁!
Moving right along, with our esteemed judges...
下面 隆重介绍我们尊敬的裁判...
Masters Steerns, Van Wyck...
斯蒂恩斯大师 范维克大师
and, rejoining our fair city after a long absence...
还有 我们久违的...
Michel La Grande.
米歇尔·拉格兰德
Please, Master La Grande, say a few words and announce the winner, please.
请拉格兰德先生大师并宣布获胜者 有请
Mayor Kessler.
凯斯勒市长
Perhaps it's better if Master Steerns speaks.
也许让斯蒂恩斯大师来说会更好
Nonsense!
胡说!
"Wisdom before beauty," or whatever.
"智慧胜于美丽" 或者其他什么
Go on.
说吧说吧
It has been written:
上面这样写着
"All nations...
所有的国家
closely should you treasure your great men...
都应密切的关注 重视伟大的人们...
for by them alone will the future know you. "
因为未来的人将通过他们来了解我们的时代
In this our city has been wise.
就这点而言 我们所在城市是非常明智的
She glorified her greatest son during his life...
她最伟大的儿子终其一生都在接受她的赞美
and magnified his name after his death.
而死后他的名字更是闻名于世
Indeed, what would this city be
的确 正如市长所说
as the mayor said
如果没有艺术来鼓舞我们的人民
but a sad bundle of stones without his art to spark its citizens.
那这座城市将会是一堆可悲的石块
As we who teach art know
我们教授艺术的应该明白
technique can be acquired...
技巧可以习得...
but real, true talent...
但真正的才华...
is a gift...
是一种天赋...
only from God.
只由上帝所赐
This year my vote went to the most talented boy...
今年我的一票将投给目前我所遇见的...
I've ever come across.
一个最有才华的少年
His dynamic painting exhibited vision...
他的画动态地展现出一种景象
and a comprehension way beyond his years.
以及一种超出他年龄的理解方式
He means me.
他在说我呢
But I am just a single vote, and this boy...
但我只有这一张选票 而这个男孩...
Yes, well, it is getting late...
哦 够了 时候不早了...
and I believe that what Master La Grande means to say...
我相信拉格兰德大师想说的...
is...
是...
that the winner...
获胜者...
is a young artist whose potential is immense.
是一个有着巨大潜力的年轻艺术家
Master Robert Kessler.
罗伯特·凯斯勒
Good work!
真漂亮!
It's over, Patrasche.
结束了 帕奇
It's over.
没有了
It's all over.
一切都结束了
We've got nowhere to go.
我们无家可归了
No one wants us anymore.
没有人会收留我们
Come on. It's cold.
走吧 这里太冷了
What is it, Patrasche? What is it?
那是什么 帕奇? 什么东西?
It's a wallet.
是个钱包
Look at all this money.
这么多钱啊
Nello, Patrasche. Come in, you poor dears.
尼洛 帕奇 快进来 可怜的小家伙们
Something terrible has happened.
一定发生了什么可怕的事情
Millie, make up a big bag of food for them.
米莉 装一大袋食物给他们
Is Master Cogez here?
库格兹先生在么
- No, he's out looking for the... - This?
-不 他正在找... -这个?
Dear God, Nello! You found it.
天哪 尼洛 你找到了这个
It was Patrasche.
是帕奇找到的
It's a Christmas miracle! Thank you.Thank you, Patrasche.
真是个圣诞奇迹!谢谢 谢谢你 帕奇
Millie, Look. Isn't it wonderful?
米莉 看 这是不是非常神奇?
We won't need that food. We'll eat together,
不用准备食物了 我们要一起吃饭
and you can give the wallet yourself.
你可以亲手把钱包还给库格兹
- Dinner is almost ready. - Okay.
-晚饭差不多已经准备好了 -太好了
Come on, Nello. There's butter cookies.
来 尼洛 那有黄油饼干
Can you please give Patrasche some warm milk?
能麻烦您给帕奇一些热牛奶么?
Come on, Patrasche. Come on.
来 帕奇 过来
Good boy.
好孩子
Madame...
夫人...
please tell Master Cogez it was Patrasche who found the money.
请告诉库格兹先生是帕奇找到的钱包
He won't deny an old dog a roof over his head, will he?
他不会拒绝给一条老狗一个安身之处的 对吧?
Nicholas will be back very soon...
尼古拉斯很快就回来了...
and you and I will tell him together.
我会和你一起跟他说的
You know what? I have something for you.
知道么? 我有些东西要给你
Sit by the fire. I'll be back in a moment.
坐在火堆旁边 我马上回来
- Where did Nello go? - I don't know.
-尼洛去哪儿了? -不知道
Maybe he went home.
也许回家了
It's Nicholas. He's home. Nicholas! Nicholas!
是尼古拉斯 他回来了 尼古拉斯! 尼古拉斯!
We're ruined. Everything's gone.All those years of work.
我们完了 一切都没了 这些年的工作都白费了
- Listen to me! - I've looked everywhere for the wallet...
-听我说! -我找遍了所有地方...
and I can't find it.
但就是找不到
What is that damn dog doing here? I want him out.
那条该死的狗在这儿干嘛? 让它出去
Here! Here's your money. Take it.
给你!这是你的钱 拿着
Nello may never amount to much.But you're lucky he's such an honest boy.
尼洛也许永远不会有这么多钱 但是你应该庆幸 他是一个如此诚实的孩子
And that "damn dog" found it for you.
而正是那个"该死的狗"为你找到的钱包
And don't worry.There's not one franc missing.
不用担心 一分钱都没少
Sir?
先生?
Madam?
夫人?
You should eat something, Aloise.
你应该吃点东西 阿洛伊斯
There's something I must tell you, sir.
有件事儿我必须要告诉你 先生
Master Stephens told me that if I told you,I'd lose my job.
斯蒂芬斯大人说如果我把这件事告诉你 我将会失去我的工作
I like the job.
我喜欢我的工作
I like your family.
我喜欢您的家人
I don't care.
我不在乎了
When I think about Nello outside alone...
每当我想起尼洛独自一人在外边的时候...
What are you talking about, Millie?
你在说什么 米莉?
He didn't do it, sir.
那件事不是他干的 先生
Nello didn't cause the fire.
尼洛没有放火
How would you know?
你怎么知道的?
Because I was there, sir.
因为我当时在那里 先生
It was Master Stephens, sir.
是斯蒂芬斯大人干的 先生
It was an accident,but he did it all the same.
那是场意外 但是的确是因他而起
He was drunk.
他喝醉了
He...
他...
He lit up his pipe in the shed.
他在屋子里点燃了他的烟斗
I'm sorry.
对不起
Nicholas, what are you going to do?
尼古拉斯 你打算怎么办?
I'm going to find Nello.
我要去找到尼洛
I've done that boy a terrible wrong, Anna.
我完完全全的错怪了那个孩子 安娜
Nello!
尼洛!
- Nello, where are you? - Answer me, boy!
-尼洛 你在哪? -回答我 孩子!
Find him!
一定要找到他!
Patrasche! What are you doing here?
帕奇 你在这干什么?
This has been the coldest Christmas ever.
今年是最冷的一个圣诞节
But it hasn't chilled the hearts of our parishioners. The Lord has been bountiful.
但严寒并没有冰封教区居民的心 因为我们的主终是慷慨的
Are you ready, Patrasche?
准备好了么 帕奇
Oh, Patrasche, not enough light.
哦 帕奇 不够亮
I can't see it.
我看不到
It's even colder in here than it is outside.
这里比外边更冷
Must be the stones.
一定是因为是这些石头
It isn't long till the sun rises, Patrasche.
天快要亮了 帕奇
Once we see his masterpiece...
只要我们能看到他的杰作...
we can join Mother...
我们就能去找妈妈...
and Grandfather.
还有爷爷
The only people who still love us.
仅有的两个仍然爱我们的人
Look.
看
That's it. I'm sure Nello went to see the Rubens.
看那边 我确信尼洛会去看鲁本斯
Patrasche.
帕奇
Look.
看
Master Rubens?
鲁本斯大师
So, what do you think?
你觉得怎么样?
It's...
它
It's magnificent.
非常宏伟
I quite liked your circus painting too.
我也很喜欢你那副关于描绘马戏团的油画
You saw my painting?
你看到我的画了?
I've taken a strong interest in your artistic career, Nello.
我对你的艺术非常感兴趣 尼洛
But...
但是...
why didn't I win the art contest?
为什么我赢不了美术比赛
You didn't want to just win, did you?
你并不是只想要赢得比赛 对么?
No. And I can't blame you.
不 我不会怪你的
You want to be accepted, Nello.
你希望被认可 尼洛
To feel loved.
希望感受到被爱的滋味
What you want, all men seek.
你所追求的 所有人都在追寻
In 200 years from now, when people will admire our paintings...
两百年之后 当人们在赞美我们的作品时...
you really think anyone will remember that silly contest?
你真的认为还会有人记得那个愚蠢的比赛么?
Will I be a great artist?
我会成为一个伟大的艺术家么?
People will be inspired by you for years to come.
人们总有一天会受到你的启迪
I know how you feel.
我明白你的感受
I left home once...
我曾经离开家...
went to Italy for eight years.
去意大利待了8年
Then my mother got sick.
之后我的母亲生病
By the time I came back here, she was dead.
等到我回到这里时 她已经过世
My mother's dead too.
我的母亲也去世了
You were her hero.
你是她的偶像
Mary Daas. She's a very fine artist.
玛丽·达斯 她是一个很棒的艺术家
- You knew my mother? - Of course.
-你知道我的母亲? -当然
Why do you think I've taken such a strong interest in you?
不然你认为我为什么会对你这么感兴趣?
- Master? - Yes?
-大师? -什么事?
If it's all right, Patrasche and I would like to come with you.
如果可以 我和帕奇想跟您一起走
No one cares.
没人关心我
Do you really think you're not loved?
你真的认为没有人爱你么?
Then you've yet to learn to see like a true artist:
那你要学会像一个真正的艺术家一样去观察:
With your heart.
用你的心去观察
My son.
我的儿子
My beautiful son.
我漂亮的儿子
"The Lord is my shepherd.
耶和华是我的牧者
I shall not be in want.
我必不至于匮乏
He makes me lie down in green pastures.
他使我躺卧在青草地上
He leads me beside quiet waters.
领我在可安歇的水域
He restores my soul.
他使我的灵魂苏醒
He guides me in the paths of righteousness for His name's sake.
他以他的名义指引我走向正义之路
Even though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death... "
即使我走过被死亡阴影笼罩的山谷
I went to find the boy...
我去找了这个孩子
who truly deserved to win the contest...
比赛真正的获胜者...
but I was too late.
但太晚了
We were all too late, sir.
我们都来晚了 先生
Are you his mother?
您是他的母亲么?
His mother lies there.
他的母亲长眠于此
And his grandfather lies there.
还有他的祖父 在那边
The boy had no other family.
这个孩子没有其他的家人
Where is his father?
他的父亲呢?
Most people believe that Nello's father lived in another city...
大多数人认为尼洛的父亲住在另一个城市...
and that he died after Nello was born.
他在尼洛出生后就死了
And what do you believe, madam?
您相信么 夫人?
I believe what his mother confided in me.
我相信他的母亲告诉我的话
That she had been in love...
她爱上了...
with a prominent artist from this city.
来自这个城市的一个知名艺术家
I want to live my life.
我想过自己的生活
But I don't want to leave you,Grandfather, or you, Mama.
但我不想离开你们 外祖父 还有妈妈
Sweetheart.
甜心
You are loved, my son.
有人在爱着你 我的儿子
I'll always be here waiting for you.
我会一直在这里等你
Nello, we're coming for you!
尼洛 我们来找你了
Oh, no, Papa! Is he dead?
哦 不 爸爸!他死了么?
- Nello, I thought you were dead. - Aloise!
-尼洛 我还以为你死了呢 -阿洛伊斯!
I saw my own funeral.
我看到了我自己的葬礼
All of you were there.
你们都在场
Just like I see you now.
就像现在一样
Rubens was with me...
鲁本斯和我在一起...
my mother and Grandfather.
还有我的妈妈和外祖父
Forgive me, Nello, I'm sorry.Forgive me, forgive me.
请原谅我 尼洛 我很抱歉 请原谅我 原谅我
I have something.
我有些东西
This was given to me when I was your age.
这是在我和你一样年纪的时候别人给我的
I knew you'd come.
我知道您会来
Just like in my dream.
就像我的梦中一样
Did you know you taught my mother to paint?
您知道您曾经教我的母亲绘画么?
Your mother?
你的母亲?
Mary Daas, your gifted student.
玛丽·达斯 您极赋才华的学生
Mary...
玛丽...
Mary never told us...
玛丽从未告诉我们...
who you were.
孩子的父亲是谁
She was afraid of the disgrace that it would bring, and...
她害怕因为这蒙受耻辱 而且...
she was afraid that the scandal would ruin you.
她怕这丑闻会毁了你
She loved you so much.
她是如此爱你
My son.
我的儿子
Father.
爸爸
Dear God, thank you.
敬爱的上帝 感谢您
谢谢观看!
树屋字幕组-电影组
荣誉出品
\\本字幕仅供学习交流,严禁用于商业途径//